A Guide to the Virginia Commission of Economy and Efficiency, Correspondence and Reports, 1916-1918
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Commission of Economy and Efficiency, Correspondence and Reports, 1916-1918
Library of Virginia
24960
1.15 cubic feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, May 18, 1959.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Commission on Economy and Efficiency was created by an Act of the General Assembly on March 16, 1916 to make a "careful and detailed study of the organization and methods of the State and local governments of the Commonwealth" and report as to the ways "State and local government can be made efficiently and economically organized and administered." The Commission was comprised of five members: P.H Drewry, George L. Browning, J. Calvin Moss, Richard Evelyn Byrd, and LeRoy Hodges. Due to lack of resources, the Commission limited its study to State government. The Commission prepared two surveys that were completed by state agencies which were assessed and evaluated. The Commission recommended: the establishment of a formalized budget system, including a proposal for a budget law (passed in 1918); increased supervision of accounts by the State Accountant; expenditures by appropriation; a fiscal year from July 1- June 30; and uniform office hours for state agencies. The Commission was dissolved in 1918.
Scope and Content Information
This collection is comprised of the administrative papers of Colonel LeRoy Hodges, Secretary of the Commission on Economy and Efficiency. Of particular interest are the drafts of the budget law that was eventually passed in 1918, and the state agency reports submitted to the Commission. These agency reports contain a history of the agency, the duties of the agency, an organizational chart, an accounting of annual expenditures, and a listing of personnel with salary and other information. Also contained in the collection is correspondence with other members of the Commission as well as with individuals outside the Commonwealth who were asked to give their opinions and suggestions regarding the Commission's work.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Each series is arranged alphabetically.
Organization
Organized into four (4) series: Administrative correspondence, 1916-1918; Correspondence with institutions outside of the Commonwealth of Virginia, 1916-1917; State agency reports, 1916-1917; and Other items, 1917-1919.
Contents List
- Series I: Administrative correspondence, 1916-1918
  Contains correspondence among members of the Commission on Economy and Efficiency as well as with other institutions and individuals.
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Correspondence of the Commission on Economy and Efficiency, 1916-1918 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1916-1917 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Draft of proposed budget law and essay, n.d. [1918] (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Payroll data by agency, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Preliminary report, n.d. [1918] (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Series II: Correspondence with agency outside the Commonwealth of Virginia, 1916-1917
  Contains correspondence with institutions outside of the Commonwealth of Virginia. Often the correspondence is soliciting assistance with the work of the Commission.
  - Census, Bureau of, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Commerce, Dept. of, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dayton Bureau of Research, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Durand, E. Dana, University of Minnesota, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Institute for Government Research, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Institute for Public Service, New York, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Massachusetts, Commonwealth of, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Moley, Raymond, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - National Municipal League, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - National Short Ballot Organization, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - New York Bureau of Municipal Research, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Secretary of the Commonwealth, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - United State Bureau of Efficiency, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Wisconsin, University of, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series III: State agency reports, 1916-1917
  Contains reports from state agencies as requested by the Commission. Information in these reports include agency histories, lists of responsibilities, and listins of personnel employed.
  - Adjutant General of Virginia, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Agriculture and Immigration, Dept. of - Division of Markets, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Agriculture and Immigration, Dept. of - Dairy and Food Division, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Attorney General of Virginia, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Auditor of Public Accounts, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Catawba Sanatorium, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Central State Hospital, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - College of William and Mary, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Commission of Game and Inland Fisheries, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Commioner of Fisheries of Virginia, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Commissioner of Prohibition, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Convict Road Force, State, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Council of Defense, State, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Crop Commission, State, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Debt Commission, State, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Department of Agriculture and Immigration, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Eastern State Hospital, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Embalming, State Board of, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Forester, State, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Geological Survey, Virginia, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Governor's Office, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Health, State Board of, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Highway Commission, State, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Home and Industrial School for Girls, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Home for Needy Confederate Women - Monthly reports, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Hospitals, Commissioner of State, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Industrial Home School for Colored Girls, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Instruction, Superintendent of, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Insurance, Bureau of, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Labor and Industrial Statistics, Bureau of, 1916-1917 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Land Office, Register of the, 1916-1917 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Laurel Industrial School, 1916-1917 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Legislative Reference Bureau, 1916-1917 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Library, Virginia State, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Lieutenant Governor, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Medical College of Virginia, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Military Records, Dept. of Confederate, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Normal School Board, Virginia, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Normal School for Women, State - East Radford, 1916-1917 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Normal School for Women, State - Farmville, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Normal School for Women, State - Fredericksburg, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Normal School for Women, State - Harrisonburg, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Normal and Agricultural Institute - Hampton, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Optometry, State Board of, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Penitentiary, Virginia, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Public Printing, Superintendent of, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Quarantine Officer for the Elizabeth River District, State, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Secretary of the Commonwealth, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Southwestern State Hospital, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - State Agricultural High School, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - State Corporation Commission, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Tax Board, State, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Treasurer, State, 1916-1917 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Uniform State Laws, Board of Commissioners on, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - University of Virginia, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Virginia Agricultural Experiment Station, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Virginia Manual Labor School, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Virginia Military Institute, 1916-1917 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Virginia Normal and Industrial Institute, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Virginia Polytechnic Institute, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Virginia State Epileptic Colony, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Virginia State School for Colored Deaf and Blind Children, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Western State Hospital, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Series IV: Other items, 1916-1919
  Contains clippings and other materials, as well as correspondence to and from Colonel Hodges related to items other than the Commission.
  - Correspondence - not related to the Commission of Economy and Efficiency, 1917-1919 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Miscellaneous, 1917-1919 (Box 2, Folder 33)